A Guide to the Richard W. Lyman papers FA1276
Rockefeller Archive Center
Richard W. Lyman papers
1965-2004
1979-1987
Rockefeller Archive Center
Lyman, Richard W. (1923-2012)
Rockefeller Foundation
FA1276
2.62 Cubic Feet 2 standard record storage boxes, Box 1-2
Arrangement
Arranged as received.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research with Personnel materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the RAC by the Stanford University archives, 2014. The collection was transferred to RAC as Accession 2014:027.
Biographical / Historical
Richard W. Lyman was born in Philadelphia on October 18, 1923.
Lyman began his undergraduate studies at Swarthmore College in 1940, but his education was interrupted when he was drafted for military service in 1943. He served in the Army Air Forces Weather Service until 1946. He graduated from Swarthmore in 1947 and went on to complete both a master's degree and a Ph.D. in history at Harvard University.
While a doctoral student specializing in contemporary British history, he was named a Fulbright Fellow, an opportunity that allowed him to spend a year studying at the London School of Economics. He also spent his summers earning money by writing articles for The Economist.
Lyman went on to teach history at Harvard, Swarthmore, and Washington University in St. Louis. In 1958, just after the publication of his first book The First Labour Government, 1924, he accepted a position as an associate professor at Stanford University. By 1962 he had been promoted to full professor. Two years later Lyman was named Associate Dean of the School of Humanities and Sciences at Stanford, and he later served as University Provost. By 1970 he was appointed President of Stanford, a position he held for ten years, during which time he successfully increased the University's revenues and enrollment.
Lyman's tenure was also characterized by the political unrest and demands for change that affected many university campuses during this time. While he worked to diversify the student body and personally opposed the Vietnam War, as president he faced violent student protests and university sit-ins that disrupted the order of campus life. In 2009 he recounted these years in Stanford in Turmoil: Campus Unrest, 1966-1972.
Lyman was offered the presidency of the Rockefeller Foundation (RF) in 1980 following the sudden death of John Knowles. Lyman had been a member of the RF Board of Trustees for four years and had also chaired its Commission on the Humanities. He took over the Foundation during a period of continuing evolution. He led initiatives in genetic engineering in agriculture, and he oversaw the mobilization of technology to support growth in the developing world. Closer to home, the Foundation looked for ways to combat poverty in America's inner cities, and RF support encouraged multimedia artists and emerging filmmakers.
Lyman retired from the RF in 1988 and returned to Stanford University in order to help establish the Freeman Spogli Institute for International Studies. He served as the Institute's director until 1991. In recognition of Lyman's longstanding interest in the humanities and technology, in 2002 the RF allocated $500,000 to the National Humanities Center to create the Richard W. Lyman Award, which honored those who used information technology to advance the field of the humanities. This award was granted from 2002 to 2006.
Richard Lyman died of congestive heart failure in Palo Alto, California, on May 27, 2012. He was 88 years old.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of Richard Lyman's personal papers with content focused primarily on his work with the Rockefeller Foundation, including but not limited to program reviews and reports, board files and administrative records as well as policy papers and historical sketches.
- Deep Thoughts file - Officer Retreat - Scanticon - Trustees Meeting - Bellagio, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Trustee Interviews - RWL, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Trustee Interviews, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Draft Letter to AD HOC Committee for July 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence - Rockefeller Foundation, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Rockefeller Foundation - Trustees, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence - Rockefeller Foundation, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence - Rockefeller Foundation, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence - Rockefeller Foundation, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence - Rockefeller Foundation, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- RWL - Terms of Employment - Rockefeller Foundation, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted from access - Personnel material
- Presidential Search - Rockefeller Foundation, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Program Ideas, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Administration, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Congratulations - Rockefeller Foundation, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- RF Illustrated - Vol. 5, no. 1, 1980 October (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Board of Trustees - Review of Arts and Humanities and Equal Opportunity Programs, 1987 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Remarks by President Richard W. Lyman - Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, 1988 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Miscellaneous Board of Trustees, 1971-1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Personnel - Possible Appointees, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
- Personnel - VP Search, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Foundation Searches, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Personnel - Rockefeller Foundation, 1981-1987 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
- Personnel - Salaries, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Rockefeller Foundation Itineraries, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- EAD's views - Population Sciences (Box 2, Folder 29)
- RF Personal, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Reports - The Minority Female Single Parent Demonstration: Program Costs and Operations, 1988 November-December (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Reports - The Rockefeller Foundation 1913-1988 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Reports - Rockefeller Foundation President's Review and Annual Report, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Reports - Research on Philanthropy (Independent Sector), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Reports - Rockefeller Foundation Annual Report 2004 - Global Challenges, Innovative Solutions (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Reports - Rockefeller Foundation Annual Report 2003 - Expanding Opportunity (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Reports - World Military and Social Expenditures (Ruth Leger Sivard), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Reports - Daring Goals For A Caring Society: A Blueprint for Substantial Growth in Giving and Volunteering in America (Independent Sector), 1986 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Reports - Ford Foundation - Overseas Locations For The Foundation's Work, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Reports - Annual Report 1986 (Independent Sector) (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Reports - The Equal Opportunity Program: A Condensed History (Elizabeth M. Romney) (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Reports - Rockefeller Foundation Annual Report 1987 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Rockefeller Foundation - Program Pamphlets, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Rockefeller Foundation History, 1965-1980 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Equal Opportunity Program History (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Excerpt from Presidential Planning and Social Sciences Research - Mr. Hoover's Experts by Barry D. Karl (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Photocopies of articles from Minerva (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Martin E. Marty, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- The Humanities and International Understanding - Some Reflections on the Experience of the Rockefeller Foundation - Malcolm Richardson, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Women's Participation in Development and Population Policy Issues - Papers by Dr. Ieda Siqueira Wiarda (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Women's Program - T. F., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 51)